A Guide to the Records of Eastern State Hospital, 1770-2009
Library of Virginia
- Series XVI. Reports, 1842-1994., Extent: 3.9 cu. ft., 2 volumes. (Box 74-82;, Volume 155-156.)
  - Subseries A. Annual Reports, 1842-1980., Extent: 3.15 cu. ft. (Box 74-80;, Volume 155.)
    - Eastern State Hospital, 1842-1980. (Box 74-77.)
      Contains annual reports for Eastern State Hospital. The annual reports were submitted to the General Assembly by the Court or Board of Directors every year. The reports were usually compiled by the superintendent and contain financial information as well as patient-related statistics, discussions of medical techniques, equipment or employment needs, patient life, and overall management of the hospital. Also included are annual reports of two units of the hospital, the Medical Records Department and the Occupational Therapy Department. Since this is not a comprehensive collection of annual reports, it may be necessary to look elsewhere for those that are missing. In the earliest years, annual reports for state institutions were part of the rough journals of the House of Delegates (1826-1846). Later, they became part of the Governor's message and annual reports of the public officers of the state (1847-1860s). Annual reports for all of Virginia's state agencies (1860s and beyond) were bound together as "Annual Reports of Officers, Boards and Institutions of the Commonwealth of Virginia," (call no. JK3930.A21).
      - 1842. (Box 74, Folder 6)
      - 1843. (Box 74, Folder 7)
      - 1844. (Box 74, Folder 8)
      - 1845. (Box 74, Folder 9)
      - 1846. (Box 74, Folder 10)
      - 1847. (Box 75, Folder 1)
      - 1848. (Box 75, Folder 2)
      - 1849. (Box 75, Folder 3)
      - 1850. (Box 75, Folder 4)
      - 1851. (Box 75, Folder 5)
      - 1852-1853. (Box 75, Folder 6)
      - 1853-1854. (Box 75, Folder 7)
      - 1853-1854 and 1854-1855. (Box 75, Folder 8)
      - 1855-1856 and 1856-1857. (Box 75, Folder 9)
      - 1855-1857, 1857-1859 and 1859-1861. (Box 75, Folder 10)
      - 1879. (Box 75, Folder 11)
      - 1902. (Box 76, Folder 1)
      - 1903-1904. (Box 76, Folder 2)
      - 1905. (Box 76, Folder 3)
      - 1906. (Box 76, Folder 4)
      - 1907. (Box 76, Folder 5)
      - 1908-1909. (Box 76, Folder 6)
      - 1910-1911. (Box 76, Folder 7)
      - 1912-1913. (Box 76, Folder 8)
      - 1914-1915. (Box 76, Folder 9)
      - 1916-1917. (Box 76, Folder 10)
      - 1918-1919. (Box 76, Folder 11)
      - 1920-1921. (Box 76, Folder 12)
      - 1921-1922 and 1922-1923. (Box 76, Folder 13)
      - 1924-1925. (Box 76, Folder 14)
      - 1926-1929. (Box 77, Folder 1)
      - 1930-1933. (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - 1934-1936. (Box 77, Folder 3)
      - 1937-1939. (Box 77, Folder 4)
      - 1940-1942. (Box 77, Folder 5)
      - 1943-1944. (Box 77, Folder 6)
      - 1945-1946. (Box 77, Folder 7)
      - 1969-1970. (Box 77, Folder 8)
      - 1973-1974. (Box 77, Folder 9)
      - 1974-1975. (Box 77, Folder 10)
      - 1976-1977. (Box 77, Folder 11)
      - 1978-1979. (Box 77, Folder 12)
      - 1979-1980. (Box 77, Folder 13)
      - Medical Records Department, 1969-1970. (Box 77, Folder 14)
      - Occupational Therapy and Recreational Therapy Departments, 1945-1946. (Box 77, Folder 15)
    - State Hospital Board, 1937-1958. (Box 77-80.)
      Contains annual reports and some statistical supplements created by the State Hospital Board. The annual reports contain financial and operational information for the institutions under the oversight of the Board and information about the Board's activities as well. The statistical supplements were meant to accompany the annual reports of the Board. The supplements contain the tables and charts to which the reports refer.
      - 1937-1938. (Box 77, Folder 16)
      - 1939-1940. (Box 78, Folder 1)
      - 1941-1942. (Box 78, Folder 2)
      - 1943-1944. (Box 78, Folder 3)
      - 1945-1946. (Box 78, Folder 4)
      - 1947-1948. (Box 78, Folder 5)
      - 1949-1950. (Box 79, Folder 1)
      - 1954. (Box 79, Folder 2)
      - 1957-1958. (Box 79, Folder 3)
      - Statistical supplement to annual report, 1951. (Box 79, Folder 4)
      - Statistical supplements to annual reports, 1952-1953. (Box 79, Folder 5)
      - Supplement to annual report, "Sixteen Years of Progress, 1938-1954," 1954. (Box 79, Folder 6)
      - Statistical supplements to annual reports, 1955-1956. (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - Western Lunatic Asylum, 1842-1869. (Box 80.)
      Contains annual reports for Western State Hospital. The annual reports were submitted to the General Assembly by the Court or Board of Directors every year. The reports were usually compiled by the superintendent and contain financial information as well as patient-related statistics, discussions of medical techniques, equipment or employment needs, patient life, and overall management of the hospital. These reports were most likely maintained by Eastern State Hospital for reference purposes.
      - 1842 and 1844. (Box 80, Folder 2)
      - 1845-1846. (Box 80, Folder 3)
      - 1847. (Box 80, Folder 4)
      - 1848-1850. (Box 80, Folder 5)
      - 1851-1853. (Box 80, Folder 6)
      - 1855. (Box 80, Folder 7)
      - 1859. (Box 80, Folder 8)
      - 1861. (Box 80, Folder 9)
      - 1867-1869. (Box 80, Folder 10)
  - Subseries B. Miscellaneous Reports, 1923-1994., Extent: .75 cu. ft. (Box 81-82.)
    Contains a variety of reports published by several sources. The reports include comprehensive studies of the mental health system in Virginia, progress reports and correction plans, and general surveys. This series also includes reports devoted to community services, civil commitment, and serving the developmentally disabled.
    Arranged alphabetically by title of the report.
    - A Survey of the Virginia Mental Hospitals (conducted by the Mental Hospital Survey Committee), 1938. (Box 81, Folder 1)
    - Department of Research and MIS monthly report, 1989 September. (Box 81, Folder 2)
    - Final Report of the Least Restrictive Alternative Project, "A Model for the Application of the Least Restrictive Alternative Doctrine in Involuntary Civil Commitment," published by the Institute on Mental Disability and the Law and the National Center for State Courts, 1984. (Box 81, Folder 3)
    - Journal of the Senate of the Commonwealth of Virginia (Extra Session), 1923. (Volume 156)
    - Plan of Correction, Joint Commission Focused Survey (1987), 1988. (Box 81, Folder 4)
    - Progress report (submitted by Hiram Davis, M.D., Commissioner of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals), 1963. (Box 81, Folder 5)
    - Reinvestment of Resources from Facility Downsizing/Closings to Community Services: A Comprehensive Review of Reinvestment Initiatives (by Margaret Pfohl, Division of Research, Evaluation and Data Management, DMHMRSAS), 1994. (Box 81, Folder 6)
    - Report of the Task Panel on Community Support Systems, 1978. (Box 81, Folder 7)
    - Report on the Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals and the Mental Institutions, by Charles J. Duke, Jr., 1949. (Box 81, Folder 8)
    - Report on the Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals and the Mental Institutions, by Charles J. Duke, Jr., 1949. (Box 81, Folder 9)
    - Report on the State Mental Hospitals of Virginia (made by the Central Inspection Board of the American Psychiatric Association) [copy one], 1950. (Box 81, Folder 10)
    - Report on the State Mental Hospitals of Virginia (made by the Central Inspection Board of the American Psychiatric Association) [copy two], 1950. (Box 82, Folder 1)
    - State Department of Public Welfare progress report, 1937. (Box 82, Folder 2)
    - Summary of Philosophical Statements on Community-Based Services: Virginia Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services System, 1949-present, 1991. (Box 82, Folder 3)
    - Summary Report on Mental Aftercare Nursing, 1967-1968. (Box 82, Folder 4)
    - Training Program Survey of Paraprofessional Skills for Serving the Developmentally Disabled, final report, 1974. (Box 82, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Comprehensive Mental Health Services Plan for Fiscal Years 1976-1981, vol. 1, 1978. (Box 82, Folder 6)
    - Virginia State Hospitals for Mental Patients: Report on Receiving System and Hospitalization Needs (prepared by the State Department of Public Welfare), 1934. (Box 82, Folder 7)
- Series XVII. Rules, Regulations and Procedures, 1841-1979., Extent: .225 cu. ft., 1 volume. (Box 83;, Volume 157.)
  Contains by-laws, rules and regulations for various aspects of Eastern State Hospital's operation including ward conduct and certain accounting procedures. The by-laws pamphlet contains detailed job descriptions for the hospital's main employees, as does the 1841 pamphlet devoted to rules and regulations. For additional information on employees, please see Series XIII. Personnel Records.
  - By-laws of Eastern Lunatic Asylum, 1852. (Box 83, Folder 1)
  - Rules and regulations, Order book of, 1876-1906. (Volume 157)
  - Storeroom and stock control accounting procedures, Manual of, 1954. (Box 83, Folder 2)
  - System of rules and regulations for the Eastern Lunatic Asylum, 1841. (Box 83, Folder 3)
  - Ward manual, 1979. (Box 83, Folder 4)
- Series XVIII. Scrapbooks, 1946-1991., Extent: 4.375 cu. ft., 42 volumes. (Box 84-94;, Volume 158-201.)
  Restricted: in their entirety, photographs featuring patients that are less than 125 years old (no redaction).
  Contains scrapbooks created and maintained by an unknown person or office at Eastern State Hospital. Most of the scrapbooks contain only newspaper clippings of articles pertaining to the hospital and pertinent mental health topics. In some cases photographs, event programs and other memorabilia are included in the scrapbooks as well. The scrapbooks are generally in fair condition, though the newspaper is yellowed and brittle. Several scrapbooks were dismantled and put into boxes to prevent further damage. In addition to the general hospital scrapbooks, one scrapbook pertaining to the library and one to the Children's Unit are also available.
  Arranged chronologically by date of scrapbook.
  - 1946 June-1948 February. (Box 84)
  - 1948 February-1949 September. (Box 85)
  - 1949 September-1950 June. (Box 86)
  - 1950 June-1951 February. (Box 87)
  - 1951 March-1952 January. (Box 88)
  - 1952 January-October. (Box 89)
  - 1952 November-1953 August. (Volume 158)
  - 1953 August-1954 January. (Volume 159)
  - 1954 January-August. (Volume 160)
  - 1954 September-December. (Volume 161)
  - 1959 October-1960 June. (Volume 162)
  - 1959 January-1967 May. (Box 90)
  - 1960 June-1961 January. (Volume 163)
  - 1961 January-May. (Volume 164)
  - 1961 May-September. (Volume 165)
  - 1961 September-1962 February. (Box 91)
  - 1962 February-August. (Box 92)
  - 1962 August-1963 March. (Box 93)
  - 1963 April-July. (Volume 166)
  - 1963 July-December. (Volume 167)
  - 1964 January-1966 August. (Box 90)
  - 1964 January-May. (Volume 168)
  - 1964 June-1965 January. (Volume 169)
  - 1965 February-October. (Volume 170)
  - 1965 June-1966 February. (Volume 171)
  - 1966 May-September. (Volume 172)
  - 1966 October-1967 February. (Volume 173)
  - 1967 February-June. (Volume 174)
  - 1967 June-September. (Volume 175)
  - 1967 October-1968 May. (Box 94)
  - 1968 February-1971 December. (Box 90)
  - 1968 June-December. (Volume 176)
  - 1968 December-1969 June. (Volume 177)
  - 1969 July-1970 January. (Volume 178)
  - 1969 July-1970 December. (Box 95)
  - 1970 January-March. (Volume 179)
  - 1970 March-August. (Volume 180)
  - 1970 August-December. (Box 95)
  - 1970 December-1971 May. (Box 96)
  - 1971 May-September. (Volume 181)
  - 1972 January-1979 December. (Volume 182)
  - 1979 January-June. (Volume 183)
  - 1979 July-1980 February. (Volume 184)
  - 1980 January-1981 December. (Volume 185)
  - 1980 March-1981 May. (Volume 186)
  - 1981 June-1982 February. (Volume 187)
  - 1982 March-1983 May. (Volume 188)
  - 1983 June-1984 May. (Volume 189)
  - 1984 June-1985 January. (Volume 190)
  - 1985 January-June. (Volume 191)
  - 1985 May-December. (Volume 192)
  - 1986 January-1987 May. (Volume 193)
  - 1987 May-December. (Volume 194)
  - 1987 October-1989 August. (Volume 195)
  - 1988 February-December. (Volume 196)
  - 1989 April-September. (Volume 197)
  - 1990 January-June. (Volume 198)
  - 1990 June-September. (Volume 199)
  - 1990 September-1991 February. (Volume 200)
  - Children's Unit scrapbook 1978-1982. (Box 94)
  - Library scrapbook, 1948-1950. (Volume 201)
- Series XIX. Theses, Dissertations and Projects, 1949-2003., Extent: 1.35 cu. ft. (Box 97-99.)
  Contains a variety of thesis papers, dissertations and projects pertaining to Eastern State Hospital and mental health topics generally. Many of the papers were written using Eastern State and its patients as part of a case study, while others highlight the contribution of Galt family members to the hospital. Other topics include psychopharmacology, schizophrenia, and the admission of children. If the name of the writer's school was available, it was included in the description. Many of the papers were written by students at local universities such as Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond, and The College of William and Mary in Williamsburg.
  Arranged alphabetically by the author's last name.
  - Bonilla, Doris W., "Mary Arnet Galt: Matron of Eastern State Hospital," thesis/paper, unknown institution, 1990. (Box 97, Folder 1)
  - Brandt, Eileen A. and Spencer, C. Edgar, "The Role and Function of Psychiatric Social Workers as Perceived by Members of Other Professional Disciplines," thesis, Virginia Commonwealth University, 1969. (Box 97, Folder 2)
  - Caminer, Vicki B., "Self-Concept, Self-Consciousness, Repression and Projection in Reactive and Process Paranoid Schizophrenics," dissertation, Virginia Consortium for Professional Psychology, 1987. (Box 97, Folder 3)
  - Carrai, Amelia L., "Cognitive Abilities in Emotionally Disturbed Children," thesis, Old Dominion University, 1987. (Box 97, Folder 4)
  - Deason, Beatrice E., "A Historical Perspective of the Mentally Ill in the United States: With an Emphasis on the Homeless Mentally Ill," thesis, Lesley College, 1993. (Box 97, Folder 5)
  - Douthit, Nathan and Wyatt, Ruth T., "Critical Incidents in the Hospitalization of Patients at Eastern State Hospital, Williamsburg, Virginia: A Comparison and Contrast of Incidents as Identified by Patients and Relatives/Non-relatives," thesis, Richmond Professional Institute, 1965. (Box 97, Folder 6)
  - Everline, Mary E., "Choice and the Meaningfulness of Activities," project, Virginia Commonwealth University, 1986. (Box 97, Folder 7)
  - Goodman, Ronald W., "The Effects of Covert Modeling and Progressive Relaxation on the Locus of Control Orientation and Drinking Behavior of Inpatient Alcohol Abusers," dissertation, The College of William and Mary, 1981. (Box 97, Folder 8)
  - Hargadon, Sue E., "The Relevance of Social Isolation to the Community Tenure of Former Mental Patients," thesis, The College of William and Mary, 1981. (Box 98, Folder 1)
  - Johnson, Diane E., "Word Association and Schizophrenia Symptomatology," thesis, The College of William and Mary, 1990. (Box 98, Folder 2)
  - Kurzer, Melvin and Lowry, Lolita L., "A Study of Admission, Diagnosis, Personal and Family Characteristics of Patients Admitted to the Children's Unit, Eastern State Hospital, January 1, 1963 through December 31, 1963," thesis, Richmond Professional Institute, 1964, [copy 1]. (Box 98, Folder 3)
  - Kurzer, Melvin and Lowry, Lolita L., 1964, [copy 2]. (Box 98, Folder 4)
  - Lombard, Judith, A., "Institutionalism in a State Mental Hospital: A Study of Institutionalism Based on Findings from 128 Patients of West Dunbar Building #7, A Chronic Women's Ward of Eastern State Hospital, Williamsburg, Virginia," thesis, Virginia Commonwealth University, 1969. (Box 98, Folder 5)
  - Morris, Jacqueline W., "Failure of Psychiatric Patients in Adult Homes: A Behavioral Analysis," thesis, The College of William and Mary, 1987. (Box 98, Folder 6)
  - Nissim-Sabat, Denis, et. al., "John Minson Galt II's Proposal to Transfer Women from Eastern Lunatic Asylum," thesis/paper, Mary Washington College, undated. (Box 98, Folder 7)
  - Oberta, Gail M., "Characteristics of Multiple and Single Admission Patients at a State Mental Hospital," thesis, University of Minnesota, 1977. (Box 98, Folder 8)
  - Powell, C. Michael, "Relationships Among Skin Conductive Activity, Averaged Evoked Potential Amplitude, and Behavior in Chronic Schizophrenia, thesis, The College of William and Mary, 1976. (Box 99, Folder 1)
  - Riley, Anne K., "The Effects of Defensive Orientation on Stress Reduction for Paranoid and Nonparanoid Schizophrenics," thesis, The College of William and Mary, 1973. (Box 99, Folder 2)
  - Siske, James H., "A History of the Eastern State Hospital of Virginia Under the Galt Family, 1773-1862," thesis, The College of William and Mary, 1949. (Box 99, Folder 3)
  - Smith, Carolyn W., "Cooperative and Supportive Conversational Behavior of Female Alzheimer's Patients," thesis, The College of William and Mary, 1989. (Box 99, Folder 4)
  - Tuntiya, Nana, "The Deinstitutionalization Movement in the Mental Health System in the U.S.," thesis [on 3.5 inch disk], 2003. (Box 99, Folder 5)
  - Weinstein, Steven E., "Sensitivity to Nonverbal Communication Among Schizophrenic Subtypes," thesis, The College of William and Mary, 1981. (Box 99, Folder 6)
  - Wolfe, Corinne A., "Psychopharmacology: The Effects of Fulfillment of Expectations on Attitudes Toward Medication," thesis, The College of William and Mary, 1975. (Box 99, Folder 7)
  - Unknown author, "Eastern State Hospital and the Third Revolution in Psychiatry" Dr. John Galt's Advanced Therapeutic Community in Williamsburg, 1841-1862," thesis/paper, unknown institution, undated. (Box 99, Folder 8)